CURRICULUM VITAE

MD. Taraq Rhaman

Present Address: 351/3, East Kazipara, Mirpur, Dhaka

Mobile: 01830539709 | 01516187421

E-mail: taraqr9@gmail.com

Github Linkedin



Professional Objective

Experienced PHP and Laravel Developer with over 4 years of expertise. Specialized in crafting robust, efficient, and secure web applications. Dedicated to delivering clean, user-centered solutions and committed to enhancing project success through a combination of technical proficiency and a strong focus on exceptional user experiences.

Special Qualification

Experienced Back-End Developer with strong attention to detail and problem-solving abilities. Designing APIs, online applications, and databases with confidence. Expert in coding, software development, application upgrades, maintenance, and code quality for maximum performance.

Education

- Bangladesh University of Business and Technology Computer Science & Engineering (2017-2021)
- Urea Sarkar Khana School and College
 - o HSC: Science (2013 2015)
 - o SSC: Science (2011 2013)

Work Experience

<u>Beximco</u>/ Software Engineer (February 2024 – Running) Key responsibilities:

- Initiate projects from scratch, building a robust development framework.
- Gathered requirements from clients to design scalable database structures.
- Apply best practices to optimize performance and maintainability.

Projects: STL Bond, CRM (Client, Ticketing, Dynamic Sidebar, Planned Work Request, and more modules)

Technologies and Languages: PHP, Laravel, MySQL, JavaScript

<u>Jatri Service Limited</u>/ Software Engineer (January 2023 – December 2023)

Key responsibilities:

- Analyze industry trends and requirements, break down their requirement, prepare estimations, and exceed expectations by delivering ahead of schedule.
- Efficiently configured Docker and created development-specific Docker files.
- Optimizing queries for enhanced performance.
- Worked with a ticketing module that served 10 million people.
- Implemented with Service Oriented Architecture.
- Managing projects with quality delivery.

Projects: User engagement, Applicant Tracking System

Technologies and Languages: PHP, Laravel, Docker, Nginx, Redis, MySQL, JavaScript, Vue JS, Firebase

<u>The CellTech</u>/ Software Engineer (July 2022 – March 2023)

Key responsibilities:

- Communicate with potential clients to understand their needs, break down requirements, prepare estimations, and propose.
- Database design and application architecture.
- Develop restful APIs for mobile apps.
- Solving bug issues and some customizations.
- Adding features to existing projects and modifications.
- Seamlessly multitasking across projects while consistently delivering top-notch quality.

Projects: Multi-tenant e-commerce, Inventory management system, Online exam platform

Technologies and Languages: PHP, Laravel, Docker, MySQL, JavaScript

JoulesLabs/Software Engineer (August 2021 - June 2022)

Key responsibilities:

- Analyzed product requirements for project clarity and developed software from scratch.
- Validated databases with comprehensive test cases.
- Developed RESTful APIs for web and mobile apps.
- Proficient in Service-Oriented Architecture for scalability.

Projects: Communication with I/O device, Time management system

Technologies and Languages: PHP, Laravel, Docker, MySQL

Technical Skills

- PHP
- Laravel, Laravel Nova, Filament
- Docker
- NginX
- Redis
- MySQL
- Javascript
- Vue 3
- Google Chrome Extension Development
- (
- C++

Certificate

Training title: Mobile Application Development

Institute: Basis Institute of Technology & Management (BITM)

Duration: 3 Months

Project Experiences

- <u>Cloud Copy:</u> Seamlessly transfer text, images, and more between devices. Enjoy cross-platform content sharing for ultimate convenience. Where my responsibility was
 - Integrated WebSocket for broadcasting events.
 - Designed and developed an intuitive admin panel using Laravel Nova
 - Added a user-friendly feedback collection feature

Technologies: PHP, Laravel, Laravel Nova, MySQL

- <u>Blogapi Docker:</u> Dockerized Laravel BlogAPI with Sanctum and Social Login.
 - Dockerized the foundational system of the BlogAPI Web for efficient deployment and scalability.
 - Leveraged Laravel with Sanctum for secure CRUD (Create, Read, Update, Delete) functionality within the API.
 - Integrated social credential-based login, enhancing user authentication options for a more versatile user experience.

Technologies: Docker, Nginx, PHP, Laravel, MySQL

- Women & E-commerce: This is a women's e-commerce site where I worked with
 - Implemented a multi-tenant system to serve multiple online stores on a single platform.
 - Created an admin panel, where the admin can change site settings like
 - Colors for nav bar, header, footer,
 - CRUD new product
 - Edit page info like about us, contact us, terms and conditions, etc.
 - Add/update banner

User site (where the user can place an order for any product)

Technologies: PHP, Laravel, MySQL

- Tab Lock Forever (<u>Live on Chrome Web Store</u>): A Chrome extension that automatically reopens and pins closed tabs when Chrome restarts, ensuring key tabs are restored
 - Allows users to add URLs for persistent tab reopening and pinning upon browser restart.
 - Includes features for efficient tab management and customization, enhancing user workflow.

Technologies: JavaScript, Chrome Extension API, HTML, Tailwind CSS,

• <u>Vue-Weather-App</u>: The Weather App is a web application that provides current weather information based on your selected location. It also suggests 5 nearby places you can visit. The app uses Vue.js for the front end and fetches weather data from WeatherAPI.com and location data from GeoDB Cities API through RapidAPI.

Technologies: Vue JS, Tailwind CSS, Weather API, GeoDB API

Extra-Curricular Activities

In the BUBT Intra University Programming Contest, I've placed second twice in a row.

Personal Details

Father's Name : Md. Moshiur Rahman

Mother's Name : Khodeza Khatun

Date of Birth : 01/01/1998

Gender : Male Religion : Islam

Marital Status : Unmarried
Nationality : Bangladeshi

Blood Group : A+

Residence Phone : 01830539709 | 01516187421

Present Address

351/3, East Kazipara, Mirpur, Dhaka

References

Name: Nahid Hasan Limon

Designation: Senior Software Engineer

Company: Jatri

Mobile: 01621316727 E-mail: nhlimon@gmail.com Name: MD Nazmul Alam

Designation: Software Engineer **Company:** AwesomeMotive

Mobile: 01789983313 E-mail: malam@am.co